- Hey folks, and welcome
to the video on HSB
or hue, saturation, brightness.
HSB is one of the many systems
that people use to name individual colors.
It's not the most common system,
I would say that RGB or hex,
you may have heard of
either or both of those,
are more common ways
of talking about color,
but HSB in my opinion,
is the most practical
and the most intuitive.
So for those reasons, it
is kind of the foundation
of the learn UI design color system.
How I'm gonna be teaching
you to think about
and to use color in this course.
Now, if you've used HSB before,
half this video is a by
you can just skip ahead,
past the point where
I explain what HSB are
and to the part where
I start talking about
how white and black are not
opposites in this color system.
But you can watch the whole
thing through anyways.
As always, I'm gonna try
and be very practical
in the examples and how
I give information here.
And so it's a little theoretical
but we will very quickly be
into the practice of things.
Let's get started.
So the first thing I'm gonna
do is change my color system
in Figma to HSB.
If you haven't done that,
just pick any layer,
go to where RGB or hex is mentioned here
and just slide on down to HSB.
And what I have now are three numbers,
there's actually four but this fourth one
is just the opacity and it's
much simpler to understand
than all the other three.
These first three numbers are HSB,
hue, saturation and brightness.
And we're gonna talk
about what they each mean.
The first is hue.
Hue is a number that is on a scale
from a minimum of the
zero to a maximum of 360.
And if I just press Shift + Up Arrow,
I can skip by increments of 10
all the way through
the range of hues here.
Now, did you notice something interesting?
As I was doing that, I'll
go all the way back down,
I'm also sliding across this.
So this is a hue picker
and this is exactly the same
as typing some number in there.
There's no difference between these two.
So knowing that, you
might even have a sense
of what exactly hue is.
If hue is on a scale from zero to 360,
like I don't know, the
degrees in a circle,
or that circle being the color wheel,
hue is actually kind of the property
that represents where you
are on the color wheel.
Like what color of the rainbow does,
whatever color we're talking about,
most closely correspond to?
Now, it's independent of
kind of the exact shade
that you're using, all of
these are the same hue.
They're the hue of zero.
Which is kind of centered,
that is a pure red.
And like you might expect, a hue of 360
this is a pure red as well.
A hue of zero and a hue of 360
are exactly the same thing.
There is zero difference between them.
In between those two numbers
is where we get every other hue though.
And most notably, green
is centered just at 120,
and blue is centered at 240.
So they sort of split the color wheel
into three even parts.
From red to green, green to
blue, and blue back to red.
Now what I wanna do is just
mention a little practical note
about each of these three
properties as I explain them.
So one thing I'll say is,
hue is really fantastic
in practice for just kind of coming up
with a more interesting
variation on a color.
So let's say that I have some red.
It's just kind of a very normal red,
and maybe it's for an error message.
One way that I'll frequently use hue,
is if I say, hey, you know what?
This error message, it kinda feels boring.
Maybe my app is supposed
to be pretty chill
and relaxed, and this feels very intense
and in your face.
I'm just gonna try bending
the hue a little bit.
I'm gonna say, I'm gonna
move it up 10 degrees,
move it up even 20 degrees.
Now, I'm almost more towards orange,
it's kinda still recognizable as red
especially if this is
clearly an error message
or I have some little icon that says,
"Hey, this is an error."
Likewise, I could move
the hue down, right?
Now, as from zero degrees,
I can't actually move it down directly.
Got to go over to 360,
and then I can move it down
10 degrees, 20 degrees,
and now I'm getting
pretty close to a pink.
And that doesn't necessarily
look like an error.
But the thing is I don't
have to be full on pink.
I can kinda have a red that
has a hint of pink in it.
And so that's what hue is really good for.
Is coming up with those
slightly different variations
where you just kinda
wanna play with something,
make it a little more interesting,
make it match your brand
just a little bit more.
Now let's talk about saturation.
Saturation is the second property.
And while hue goes from zero to 360,
saturation actually only
goes from zero to 100.
So again, I'm gonna
slide in there, go to 0%,
watch what happens when
I hold Shift + Up Arrow
and go to 100.
Now I'm at this very
rich kind of red here.
Let me go back down.
Be-oop! It's gone, I'm back to gray.
And so saturation works like this.
0% saturation is always gray.
It's always gonna be
some shade of gray, look.
It might even be white, it might be black,
it could be something
that we traditionally
refer to as gray.
And by the way, every single
time I say gray in this course,
I virtually always mean
white and black inclusive.
It's much more logical and useful
from a designer's perspective
if white and black are included in gray.
And that's true here.
A saturation of zero will
always give me some gray.
As I increase it towards 100,
I'm gonna kind of inject
color into the gray.
That's a good way to think about it.
Let's go see some other hues here.
Now I'm at one 12.
I'm removing the color
until all I have is gray
and then I'm injecting the color back in.
So 100% saturation is kind of
like the maximum amount of color
that I can inject into that gray.
Another word that you
will hear me use a ton
in describing saturation is richness.
I often will describe
a fully-saturated color
or a very saturated
color as being very rich.
And this is being kind of dull or flat.
It's not essential that you
have to start talking like that
but it can be useful to kind of
build up your design vocabulary
and understand some terms to
describe those sorts of things.
Now in practice, here's
my little practical tip
about saturation.
It is something that is
often used if for instance,
something feels like it's just too much.
Like, you know, with this red,
I might feel, "Wow, this
red is just too much
for whatever the particular setting is."
Again, if it's kind of supposed to be
a little bit more chill of an app.
So a lot of times when
something feels like too much
or too eye-popping, or it's
searing itself into my eyes,
I'm gonna go and I'm gonna
reduce that saturation.
And if I do it too quickly,
it's just gonna look like
it's kind of fading out here
that's not the goal,
you kinda have to blink
and reassess and say,
"You know what? This
red with 70% saturation
actually feels a lot better
compared to this blazing red right here."
So that's one useful thing
to know about saturation.
The third property, fortunately
is the most obvious one.
So we're ending very easy here.
I'll just go pick another random hue here.
The third property is brightness.
And like saturation,
brightness goes on a
scale of 0% brightness
all the way up to 100% brightness.
Back down to zero and back up to 100.
And you may be noticing something
that's kind of a little interesting here.
0% brightness is black and
100% brightness is not white.
We're actually gonna come
back to that in just a sec.
Instead you should think
of brightness more like
kind of having a light
bulb in a dark room.
When that light bulb is off, 0% on,
that room is pitch black.
And that's what I see right here.
As I start to turn that light
bulb on a little bit more,
it's going to light up the
room, but only so much.
It's really not gonna do all that much.
As I turn that brightness
on more and more,
it's clear that this is a blue light bulb
and it's lighting up the
room in kind of a blue hue.
But no matter how much I
turn on that light bulb,
I can get a brighter and brighter blue
but I'm never gonna get white.
There's no blue that's so strong
that it just turns into white.
That's not how color works.
So think of brightness like,
how much is that light bulb on?
Now with saturation and brightness,
you may have also noticed that
when I'm moving saturation
what's going on is I am
moving from left to right
on this color picker here.
And when I'm moving brightness,
I'm moving up and down on
this color picker here.
So I can type in three numbers here,
I can type them directly,
I can use my arrow keys,
I can paste something,
or I can change the hue
via this hue picker,
the saturation via left to right here,
and the brightness via up and down here.
All right, so that's
the fundamentals of HSB.
That's what hue, saturation
and brightness are.
If this seems a little bit complex,
I encourage you to open up your design app
and kinda play around with how HSB work,
to get a little more intuitive sense.
But now we're gonna get into
some kind of interesting points
about exactly how they work
and some of their quirky behaviors.
So the first thing I wanna talk about
is the fact that black and
white are not opposites in HSB.
And we kind of alluded to this earlier.
It's really apparent if you
look at the color picker here,
where white is just the
upper-left hand corner.
If I wanna make something white,
I have to slide loop, up to this corner.
But black is not just
the bottom left corner,
it's this entire bottom of the graph.
And what that's saying is,
in HSB, it doesn't matter
what saturation is.
If my brightness is zero, it's black.
On the other hand, if I wanna make white,
I have to do two things.
I have to make the saturation zero
and I have to make the brightness 100.
This actually has a lot of implications
for user-interface design,
which I'll show you now.
So let's say I just press
A to create new art board,
bring up an old iPhone size,
and I'm gonna go ahead
and just create some kind
of like header and whatever.
Some color here, it totally
doesn't matter what color.
And then I'm gonna put in a search bar.
So I'll press R to get a new rectangle,
I'll round off my search bar here.
And now I'm gonna make
my search bar white.
But if I decide that
I really don't want it
to be quite this eye-popping,
I could actually reduce the
opacity of the search bar.
If I reduce it to 50% here,
what that's doing is it's
blending the white of this layer,
with kind of this teal
of the background layer.
And it's actually a color
that's sort of like halfway
in-between those two colors.
It's 50% foreground and 50% background.
Interestingly enough, if you look here,
let's go look at this
color and this color.
You can see that my darker teal right here
is neatly situated right there.
A saturation of 65 and a brightness of 46.
As I add in white, even
though it's not full on white
it's kinda added to that background color.
What happens is I move
up into the left here,
which makes sense.
The white is just this point
all the way to the left
and all the way up,
and what I'm gonna do as
I add more and more white
is move towards that point from
whatever other point I'm at.
So the function of adding white
or creating a lighter variation,
is always going to entail
increasing the brightness
and decreasing the saturation.
Let's contrast that to
something like adding black.
If I take this search bar and I said,
"You know what? I don't
like the light variation."
I'm actually just gonna
make the search bar black.
Well, I have, here, I'm gonna move this
so it's not quite so much a mess here.
Here's my black search
bar, it's 50% opacity.
Let's make another little swatch
and see what is the resulting color.
Oops, I lost my first one.
What's the resulting color here?
So again, I start at saturation of 65%,
brightness of 46%.
And when I move to the darker variation,
the saturation stays the same
and the brightness goes down.
So 65, 46, 66, that's
actually a rounding error.
You can nevermind that it
goes from 65 to 66 here.
But the important bit is the
brightness goes from 46 to 23.
It basically halves.
And what that means is
on this color chart,
adding black isn't the
opposite of adding white.
Adding white means up into the left.
Adding black is just going straight down.
It's just a drop in brightness,
there's really no change
to the saturation.
The implication of this for us though,
is that we are basically never
going to be making color
variations by adding black,
because in the real world,
when you see a shadow
fall on a colored layer,
you have kind of a darker
variation of a color,
it's not the equivalent of
adding black to that color.
It's the equivalent of
removing white from the color.
And in the HSB those are different things.
We always wanna think
in terms of adding white
and removing white, not
adding white or adding black.
If we do a lot of adding
black what we'll notice is
our colors tend to end
up a little bit flat
when we make darker variations.
And instead, what we might wanna do is,
I mean, one way of doing it
is to make a hand-picked variation,
and we'll talk about others
in a little bit later,
but if I make a
hand-picked variation here,
let's bring the opacity back up to 100%.
I'm just going down in to the right
and kind of exploring
for exactly the color
that feels good there.
And that's gonna be much more natural
than just having say some
flat black layer here
with a reduced opacity.
You can see there's a little
bit more richness to this one
than there is to this one.
Now one final point about HSB
and how they all kinda work together.
And that is, saturation
actually works slower
for darker colors.
So if I had some element,
I'm just gonna like pick a card here.
Although I just need something
on the screen to show you,
I don't actually recommend
making cards like this.
Let's say I have a very
bright card, 93% brightness,
I can even go higher 98, 99, whatever.
There's 96, that's fine.
Now I'm gonna use this
same hue that I have 176,
that's gonna kinda make
everything feel matching
and put together.
And what I'm gonna do is
I'm gonna add in saturation,
I'm gonna take this gray,
and I'm gonna inject this hue into it
until I can kind of just barely see it.
And the idea is like when
would I kind of identify,
"Oh yeah, that is definitely
that same sort of aquamarine color."
And actually it feels like
now is about that time.
This is a hue of six.
This isn't an exact science,
it's just, I'm kinda saying,
"Okay when can I like
pretty easily feel that
that is gonna be that same aquamarine?"
Now, all I had to add in
was the saturation of six
before I felt like that gray
had a very distinct color to it.
That is not how it works
with darker colors.
And one example of this
is let's say I have some
kinda like sidebar menu that comes in here
for my mobile app.
I'm gonna grab that same hue,
I'm actually gonna,
well I'm gonna remove the
saturation to begin with,
but we'll add it back in.
But this time I'm gonna
make it much darker.
Like let's say like 20%
or something, even 15.
Now, as I add in the saturation,
let's watch what happens.
I'm at four or five, six.
At 6% saturation, I still
cannot distinguish this
from a totally flat gray.
So I added more.
Here's 12, 13, still nothing,
still appears very gray.
24, okay, now I'm just gonna go up by 10.
34, 44.
Okay, 44 is sort of the first time
where I feel like, "Ah,
yeah, there's some green
in this gray. I can see
what's going on here."
Well, this is not an exact measure, right?
I'm just, again, kind of
eyeballing it and saying,
"I'm just saturating this,
I'm just injecting color in
until I can kinda barely notice it."
It's not like these are
equivalently saturated
or like some level of visual saturation,
but that's kinda what I'm going for here.
And the important takeaway,
is when you're working
with a very bright color,
towards the top here, you
actually don't have to add in
very much saturation at all
for it to be kind of apparent.
But when you're working
with a very dark color,
you can add in a shocking
amount of saturation
and it's not gonna look crazy.
Here we are at 74% saturation.
If I took this card and brought
it up to 74% saturation,
(laughs) you can see it's
like quite rich and strong.
It's really not even the
same feel at all anymore.
And that wraps it up for HSB.
Now, whether or not
you've used this system
whether you're already
kind of an expert at it,
or even if you're just seeing
it for the first time today,
go ahead and take a
look at today's homework
which is to play a game.
And this game is a guessing game
and it's gonna help you kind of
forge a deeper mental connection
between values of HSB,
those three numbers,
and the actual color that they generate.
And that is only a good thing.
The goal is that you would
be able to look at any color
and not only have a sense of roughly
what the HSB values are,
but eventually you will see a color,
know how you wanna change it,
know which of those
properties you need to change,
and by roughly what amount.
Now it's a long road,
but you will get there.
And we are going to be
spending a lot of time
going very deep on HSB.
So all of this stuff
is foundational things
that we will very much be
building on in future videos.
All right, take a look at the homework.
Feel free to post high scores
in the student community
and we'll see you in the next lesson.